<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An impartial examination and refutation of the erroneous tenents of Thomas Moor in his dangerous writings intituled Clavis Aurea &amp;c. wherein he is not ashamed to insinuate his being the Elias mentioned in Malachi, denies an Hell, or future punishment, and boldly asserts the inevitable salvation of all men.</title>
            <author>T. C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31280</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C135</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35832</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15564738</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15564738</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103796</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31280)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103796)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1588:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An impartial examination and refutation of the erroneous tenents of Thomas Moor in his dangerous writings intituled Clavis Aurea &amp;c. wherein he is not ashamed to insinuate his being the Elias mentioned in Malachi, denies an Hell, or future punishment, and boldly asserts the inevitable salvation of all men.</title>
                  <author>T. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader signed": T.C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Moore, Thomas, --  Junior. --  Clavis aurea.</term>
               <term>Hell.</term>
               <term>Salvation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103796:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN Impartial EXAMINATION AND REFUTATION OF THE <hi>Erroneous Tenents</hi> OF THOMAS MOOR; In his dangerous Writings, intituled, CLAVIS AUREA, &amp;c. Wherein he is not aſhamed to infinuate his being the <hi>Elias</hi> mentioned in <hi>Malachi;</hi> denies an Hell, or future Puniſhment, and boldly aſſerts the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable Salvation of all Men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> the lower End of <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers Chapel.</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:103796:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103796:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NOT doubting but I have expoſed my ſelf to the Cenſure of ſome, for taking notice of ſo inconſiderable a Writer, and endeavouring to refute Errours ſo obvious to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of every perſon that hath learned but the Alphabet of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, I think my ſelf obliged to prefix the Reaſon of my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking this unpleaſant Task. I have been divers times aſſaulted by a particular Friend, of long acquaintance, with theſe pernicious Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of <hi>Thomas Moor;</hi> who, having been unhappily ſeduc'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is grown ſo great an Advocate, as not only with great Zeal to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, but diſperſe them very induſtriouſly with his own hands in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers parts of the Country: and after ſome endeavours by perſonal Conference to recover him (tho' with too little appearance of ſucceſs) he earneſtly deſired me to make particular Remarks in writing for his and others ſatisfaction; expreſſing at the ſame time a willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to recede, if I or any other perſon could fairly overthrow thoſe defended Principles which he eſteem'd impregnable. Tho' I did not readily, nor the firſt ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e in any meaſure, comply with his requeſt (having always had an averſion to the Polemical part of Theology, of which, if I miſtake not, the World is too full already); yet upon further thoughts, together with the obſervation of <hi>T. M</hi>'s. inſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrain, becauſe his Books were never yet anſwered, I did at laſt endeavour it: and becauſe ſome (of better Judgment than my ſelf) have thought my Remarks worthy of publick view, as being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apted to the preſent Atheiſtical Times, I have ſubmitted my own mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Opinion to theirs in that behalf; and heartily deſire they may, through Divine Bleſſing, in ſome degree anſwer the end for which they are (I hope ſincerely) intended. I have not the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to think them ſo correct, as ſo ſecure me from the laſhes of cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Criticks, there having been ſcarce ten days paſs'd ſince I firſt undertook thus to gratifie my Friends Curioſity; and by reaſon of many avocations I had not leiſure to tranſcribe the blotted Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,
<pb facs="tcp:103796:3"/> which may be ſome excuſe for Errata's in Printing. I hope this ſmall Incurſion into the Province of others will not give of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, or be adjudged a breach of Priviledge; as this is the firſt time, ſo 'tis, at leaſt, probable it may be the laſt. When a Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Enemy invades our Confines, we excuſe the irregularity if others, beſide the well-diſciplin'd <hi>Militia</hi> ſet an helping-hand to oppoſe him; and when the grand Enemy appears moſt audacious to ſtrike at the Safety and Happineſs of Mankind, ſuch Liberty ſeems to be no leſs allowable: Yet I can truly ſay, I had much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have ſit ſtill, and ſeen ſome other perſon of better capacity engag'd herein. What, with the increaſe of Atheiſm and Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality (too much conniv'd at heretofore) on the one hand, and an exorbitant Zeal for promoting Parties and Opinions on the other, that the Antient Footſteps of Chriſtian Piety and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Charity have been greatly obſcur'd, and are in no ſmall dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being totally defac'd, is the ſad experience of Reformed Chriſtendom at this day: And 'twere heartily to be wiſh'd, that all who ſincerely profeſs and agree in the Fundamentals of the ſame Faith, would forget their former and preſent Heats, bitter In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives and terms of diſtinction (as Deformities unfit to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with them into the other World) and every one become emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of ſetting the firſt ſtep towards an hearty Reconciliation: This ſeems to be the beſt Expedient againſt the deſtructive Wiles of the common Adverſary, and far more honourable than to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, with a partial Reſolution, the utmoſt extent of their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral fortified Opinions in ſuch things as themſelves own to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meerly indifferent, or, at moſt, not eſſential to Salvation. But, kind Reader, pardon my boldneſs and prolixity. That the ſame Omnipotent Goodneſs which once diſpos'd the Original Chaos into Order and Harmony, would at laſt effectually interpoſe to heal our manifold Breaches, and eſtabliſh Peace and Truth in our Borders, to the great Happineſs of this and ſucceeding Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, is the ſincere deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your hearty Well-wiſher, <hi>T. C.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>April 10. 1698.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:103796:3"/>
            <head>A Succinct Refutation OF THE Erroneous Tenents of <hi>Thomas Moor,</hi> In his dangerous Writings, intituled, <hi>Clavis Aurea, Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>NOT to trouble my ſelf or the Reader with a tedious recita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of, or particular deſcant upon, the many miſcellaneous expreſſions and tautologies in the ſeveral parts of this bold Author's unhappy Writings, I ſhall endeavour impartially, and in as few words as may be, to repreſent the plain ſcope of the whole, and then to make ſome very brief Remarks thereon.</p>
               <p>The Marrow therefore (or rather Venom) of theſe no leſs dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous than uncommon Notions, plainly offers it ſelf under theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. That all mankind (tho' for the moſt part living and dying in an hardened courſe of ſin and unbelief) ſhall be ſaved.</item>
                     <item>2. That Faith is given after this life to ſuch as die in impenitency and unbelief.</item>
                     <item>3. That there is no Hell, or future ſtate of eternal puniſhment; but by thoſe terms, ſo often uſed in ſacred Writ, are meant only the troubles of this life.</item>
                     <item>4. That Man in his primitive Innocency had not, nor now hath, in any meaſure, a free will or choice in himſelf: but that <hi>Adam</hi>'s fall, and the greateſt particular tranſgreſſions ever ſince, were by Divine Predeſtination and compulſion.</item>
                     <item>5. That the Children of the fleſh (<hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 8.) are all men in the fleſh, whether good or evil; and the Children of Promiſe are the Souls of all men that ever were, are or ſhall be, not one excepted of what Nation or belief ſoever) in their ſeparated or unbodied ſtate.</item>
                     <item>6. That the <hi>Elijah</hi> propheſied by <hi>Malachy</hi> is yet to come; and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103796:4"/> that the ſaid <hi>T. M.</hi> (though ſomewhat cautious with a ſeeming modeſty) is that very perſon.</item>
                     <item>7. That this extraordinary Hypotheſis had extraordinary proof of its certainty, <hi>viz.</hi> Divine Revelation; as the Viſion of a fiery tranſparent Globe, a Dove, Comet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>To begin with the firſt [—<hi>That all mankind ſhall be ſaved.</hi>—]</p>
               <p>This <hi>T. M.</hi> grounds upon (<hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 32.) and from thence infers, That all the literal Jews, though avowed Enemies to the Goſpel, and dying in unbelief, are notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding intereſted in God's Electing Love, and conſequently ſaved: Taking this for the clear meaning of that part of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Writings, and a Truth impregnable, he proceeds to confirm it by ſeveral Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and parallel Scriptures. But becauſe the forementioned Quotation from (<hi>Rom.</hi> 11.) is, and he acknowledges to be, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hinge or foundation of his Hypotheſis, I ſhall in the firſt place endeavour to touch thereupon. Therefore,</p>
               <p>Firſt; The plain ſcope of the Apoſtle in thoſe words, ſeems to be (For I dare not aſſume this bold Aſſertor's infallible ſtrain, than which no greater mark of a Satanical deluſion) That he would re-mind the converted Gentiles, of their former miſerable State whilſt Strangers to the Goſpel, and fix on them: the moſt humble ſenſe of the greatneſs of their preſent Priviledges, their own unworthineſs, and the danger of ingratitude, carnal ſecurity, and a careleſs uſing thoſe ineſtimable Talents committed to their charge. And he heightens this ſo neceſſary <hi>Momento</hi> from the tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendous Example of the obſtinate Jews, who by an exorbitant Zeal for, and confidence in the Externals of their Religion, were juſtly left to ſo great Blindneſs, as to reject, oppoſe and crucifie the true Meſſiah (the End and Center of their Typical Worſhip) whom they pretended to wait for. <note place="margin">Act 13. 27.</note> Having a little before ſpent a whole Chapter in vindicating the Divine Juſtice, in theſe great and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duous Points, againſt the bold and groundleſs Cavils of ſuch as would be ready to impeach it, the better to confirm the believing Gentiles in their Title to the Priviledges of the New Covenant; and well knowing the great propenſity of Humane Nature to Pride, Oſtentation, and Carnal Security, he does by divers Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors, and ſtrong Arguments, very pathetically endeavour to fortifie them againſt the ſame Stumbling-block, which had been ſo fatal to the other. For though theſe degenerate Branches of faithful <hi>Abraham</hi> had thus ſtubboruly and wilfully excluded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the fulneſs of their Idoliz'd promiſes; yet the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103796:4"/> being ingraffed into the ſame Root or Principle of Faith with the Primitive Jewiſh Anceſtors (who liv'd and dy'd in the true Faith of the Meſſiah) were not to inſult over them, but from their Fall ſhould rather be excited to the greater caution, humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and fruitfulneſs (as before hinted): and the rather, becauſe this rejection of the whole Unbelieving Race of literal <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is not to be eſteemed abſolute; it being very probable that God may hereafter in his due time, <note place="margin">11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24. ver.</note> and by ſome extraordinary Diſpenſation of his Providence, powerfully convince and convert a remnant of them to the Chriſtian Faith. Nevertheleſs he will not thus own or reſpect them conſidered as literal Jews, but as Goſpel Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in common with the Gentiles, both together making up the ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the true Univerſal Church peculiarly purchaſed by Chriſt, juſtified ſolely by Faith in him, and ſanctified, govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and preſerved by the happy influence and conduct of the Holy Spirit. For all (<hi>i. e.</hi> both Jews and Gentiles, which include the whole World) having ſinned, <note place="margin">verſe 32.</note> and being concluded by God in Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, as to their own natural or moral capacity, are equally made partakers of the ſame rich Mercy and free Grace of God in the Goſpel. This ſeems to be the plain drift of this profound Apoſtle, as well in the forementioned verſes at in the two former chapters, and divers other parallel places of his Epiſtles; and particularly of this to the <hi>Romans.</hi> One while he tells us <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 28.</note> —He is now a Jew that is one outwardly—; <note place="margin">ch. 9. v. 6.</note> that all, not <hi>Iſrael</hi> that are of <hi>Iſrael</hi>—: at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 15.</note> that Circumciſion availeth nothing—; and <note place="margin">ch. 3. v. 28.</note> —that there is neither Jew nor Greek, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but all are one in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>Secondly; The beſt and ſafeſt way of expounding this part of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Writings, is to compare it with the general ſcope of other Scriptures, and eſpecially with the aſſertions of the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in his other Epiſtles, who doubtleſs beſt knew his own mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. If in this, or any other part of his Writings he ever intended to ſuggeſt the certain and inevitable Salvation of all men, or that the Jews dying in Unbelief and Enmity to the Goſpel, are not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding elected and ſaved; we ſhould not find him in the ſame Epiſtle ſo pathetically lamenting their dreadful condition, as to wiſh himſelf accurſed from Chriſt for their ſakes—; <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 2, 3.</note> nor giving ſuch cautions not to treaſure up Wrath againſt the day of Wrath, and revelation of the righteous Judgment of God, who will render to every one according to their deeds—; <note place="margin">ch. 2. v. 5, 6.</note> nor would he have uſed holy policy, ſuch condeſcenſion, ſuch unwearied pains, undergone ſuch trials and hardſhips in the ſervice of his great Maſter (much dearer to him than his life,) <note place="margin">Act. 20. 24</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> propagating the Goſpel, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103796:5"/> its Converts in their holy Faith—; becoming to the weak as weak,—<hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 22.</note> that by all means he might ſave ſome—; earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exhorting them ſo to run as that they might obtain the prize—; and for their greater vigilancy and circumſpection enforcing on them the Example of his own Spiritual Warfare, by which he kept under the relicts of corruption, leſt when he had preached the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Goſpel to others, himſelf ſhould be caſt away—; <note place="margin">24, 25, 26, 27. verſes.</note> nor would he have ſpoken of the differing Effects of the ſame unchangeable Word of Life, as being the ſavour of death unto death in them that periſh, and of life unto life in them that believe and embrace it—: <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 15, 16.</note> nor yet mentioned any thing of the Goſpel being hid from ſuch as are loſt and judicially blinded by the God of this World—; <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 3, 4.</note> nor dehorted the backſliding <hi>Galatians</hi> from thoſe works of the fleſh (particularly mentioned) with a poſitive aſſertion, that all thoſe who commit ſuch things (with allowance and perſeverance) ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God—: <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 19, 20, 21.</note> nor would he have exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Church at <hi>Philippi</hi> not to be terrified by their Adverſaries, which was to them an evident token of perdition,—<hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 28</note> nor told them afterwards, with weeping, of ſome that walked contrary to the Goſpel, being Enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt, whoſe end is deſtruction—: <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 18, 19</note> nor would he have comforted the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> under their ſore troubles and perſecutions with a <hi>Memento</hi> of Chriſt's glorious Coming, to give them perfect reſt, and an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the heavenly Kingdom; as alſo to take vengeance on them that know not God, and obey not the Goſpel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction,—<hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 7. 8, 9.</note> 'Tis needleſs to enumerate the many concurring Teſtimonies of the other Apoſtles, and of our Saviour himſelf in the Records of the Evangeliſts, leſt I ſhould ſeem too tedious in a point ſo clear, that the contrary Aſſertion (as <hi>T. M</hi>'s.) muſt ſtrike at the whole ſcope of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſhew a degree of obduracy beyond compariſon. What is urged of Chriſt's giving himſelf a Ranſom for all,—<hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 6.</note> and being the Saviour of all men, but eſpecially of them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,—<hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">ch. 4. v. 10.</note> ſhall be conſidered hereafter under the fourth Head.</p>
               <p>Thirdly; This Doctrine of Univerſal and Inevitable Salvation, not only ſubverts the many harmonious Teſtimonies of Sacred Writ, but the Dictates of right Reaſon; inaſmuch as it ranks the moſt pertinacious Miſcreants hardened Sinners and inveterate Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, with the truly pious regenerate and faithful Profeſſors of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. The ſcattered Relicts of Reaſon implanted in Humane Nature, have in all Ages ſuggeſted the puniſhment and reward of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103796:5"/> Vice and Vertue, among ſuch as had not the advantage of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Oracles: And ſome of them, who lived in thoſe dark Times and Places, have been ſo exemplary in Moral Attainments, (if Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, Mortification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may not deſerve an higher Epithete) as to ſhame the far greater part of Chriſtians, though dignified with more excellent, yea ineſtimable Priviledges. <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 14, 15, 26, 27.</note> What can be more abſurd than to equal a bloody <hi>Nero,</hi> (living in the height of wickedneſs againſt God and Man, as his only Element, and dying wholly void of remorſe) with a pious ſelf-denying (I had almoſt ſaid, Divine) <hi>Seneca:</hi> or St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that great Apoſtle of the Gentiles, and unwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Inſtrument in propagating the Chriſtian Faith, with a mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious apoſtatizing and perſecuting <hi>Julian?</hi> If it be objected, that this Argument centers Man's Salvation in Works, and leſſens the Glory of God, who intends only the exaltation of Free Grace: this will be found but a very weak Subterfuge. For, as on the one hand, the beginning, progreſs and accompliſhment of the Bleſſed work of Salvation in every Soul is wholly ſupernatural, and none of the concurring faculties of Man's moſt noble rational part, when truly ſubjected to Divine Grace, may have the leaſt claim or pretence in the matter of Juſtification: <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 23, 24. Eph. 2. 8, 9.</note> So, on the other hand, that Faith which doth not work by Love, and incline the Soul to ſincere returns of Univerſal Obedience, or at leaſt deſires after it, is but empty, fictitious and unprofitable. The genuine ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of the New Birth, is to breathe in the heavenly Air. Grace effectually operating will endeavour to return ſome ſtreams, at leaſt droppings, of Love towards the immenſe Ocean from whence it came. Though the imperfect Obedience of finite Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures cannot add to, nor their moſt obſtinate Diſobedience detract from the Divine Perfection: yet we may as well imagine that the Scriptures of undoubted truth, are no better than one aggrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fallacy, and deſign'd for no other uſe than to amuſe the World, as that Mankind ſhall be ſaved upon terms differing from, or contradictory to what God himſelf hath preſcribed. If he hath enjoyn'd Faith and Obedience, and made them ſo eſſential, that without the former (which alſo includes the latter) it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to pleaſe him: <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 6.</note> Doubtleſs there can be no greater indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity offered than to imagine, yea promiſe, and as it were inſure Salvation to all ſuch as ſtubbornly perſiſt in Unbelief, Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and open Hoſtility againſt both the Author and the Terms of Grace.</p>
               <p>Fourthly; Such a Doctrine tends to the utter ſubverſion of all good Principles and Practices, whether Moral, Legal, or Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103796:6"/> and rendring the World as wicked as Satan or corrupt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can ſuggeſt. Though it muſt be acknowledged that Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Obedience is, or ought to be grounded on the ennobling Principle of Love, rather than a ſervile fear of Wrath and Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: yet ſo great is the Degeneracy of Humane Nature that there is no ſmall need of thoſe terrifying Methods, as preparatory to the ſweet Conſolations of the Goſpel: And, indeed, moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the work of Regeneration begins with the Terrours of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Convictions; which nevertheleſs do often prove abortive, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as they grow remiſs, and ſuffer a backſliding into former ſenſuality, or fix Man upon the ſandy foundation of his own feeble Performances, as the ground of his hope and confidence. But if all Mankind ſhall neceſſarily be ſaved, without any reſpect to their Obedience or Diſobedience, Faith or Unbelief; what need then of all the pains in Preaching, or propagating the ſweet and delectable ſound of the Goſpel; or of the care, ſtudy, zeal, or endeavours about Religion in the World? To what purpoſe did Chriſt leave that clear and poſitive aſſertion. That <hi>except a man be born again he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God</hi>—? <note place="margin">John 3. 3.</note> or enjoyn us to enter in at the ſtrait Gate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or tell us, that <hi>wide is the gate, and broad is the way that leads to deſtruction, and many there be that go in thereat</hi>—? <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 13.</note> What need of <hi>ſeeking firſt the Kingdom of God and the Righteouſneſs thereof</hi>—? <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 33.</note> of <hi>becoming new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi>—? <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5. 17.</note> or of <hi>growing in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt</hi>—? <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3. 18.</note> How greedily would the practical Atheiſt, (<hi>i. e.</hi> every profane diſſolute and licentious perſon (catch at ſuch a Doctrine, had he not a ſecret Remembrancer in his own boſom that deals more faithfully with him when ſuffered to ſpeak; and ſometimes without leave! To ſuch <hi>T. M</hi>'s. Notions would be the moſt welcome they ever met with, if they could but arrive at the ſame pitch of certainty as to their future Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and ſo take firſt a full carouſe in the ſweets of this World, (as they erroneouſly eſteem the height of wickedneſs and ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity) and afterwards poſſeſs the unthought of Joys of the World to come. May the laudable and united Endeavours of Superiours at this time prove effectual to the ſuppreſſing both of ſpeculative and practical Atheiſm, blaſphemous Libels, and fundamental Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, ſo audaciouſly propagated of late Years, to the great ſhame and detriment of Reformed Chriſtianity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>The ſecond Head to be examined is,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Faith is given after this Life to ſuch as dye in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:103796:6"/>
               <p>This is but a ſuperſtructure upon the ſame Foundation. For if all Men are neceſſarily ſaved; if Faith be eſſential to Salvation; and if a great part of literal <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and many others dye in Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, then Faith muſt be given after this Life. This is <hi>T. M</hi>'s. own way of arguing. <hi>Clav. Aurea. p.</hi> 9. But that this is no leſs abſurd and contradictory to the ſcope of the holy Scriptures, will eaſily appear. For,</p>
               <p>Firſt; The ſhort and uncertain Life of Man in this World, is, and ought to be eſteemed the only time of probation in order to his future ſtate. And indeed 'tis no ſmall favour, to have ſuch a gracious Reprieve from the Sentence of Eternal Death due to <hi>Adam</hi>'s Tranſgreſſion: To have the Tree of Life, though forfeited, freely exhibited again, and the former loſs in the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> recovered with unſpeakable advantage in the ſecond, by all that through Faith lay hold on him. That this Life is the only ſeaſon of Grace, is evident from the five rejected Virgins in that well known Parable of Chriſt, who had ſlipt the proper time for furniſhing their Lamps, and ſecurely deferr'd it till the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom's Coming: alſo from his ſeaſonable Caution to the Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Jews—to walk while they had the Light—; <note place="margin">Joh. 12. 35.</note> together with his aſſertion to the ſame obſtinate Jews, dying in their ſins—; <note place="margin">Joh. 8. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Whither I go ye cannot come</hi>—. As Death leaves, Judgment finds us: For if there had been any middle ſtate of probation, doubtleſs the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> would not have been altogether ſilent in this caſe, when he tells us, <hi>'Tis appointed for all men once to dye, but after this the Judgment</hi>—. <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 27.</note> And if St. <hi>Peter</hi> had thought the work of Faith and Repentance ſo indifferent in this Life, or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable in another, 'tis ſcarce probable he would have preſſed it ſo earneſtly in his Advice to the ſcattered Saints—to uſe all diligence that they might make their Calling and Election ſure—. <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Solomon</hi> adviſes to an induſtrious improvement of the preſent time, becauſe <hi>there is no knowledge nor wiſdom in the grave whither we are all haſtening</hi>—. <note place="margin">Eccl. 9 10.</note> The good King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> in his thankful acknowledgments to God after a ſignal Reprieve from the Jaws of Death (and we may ſuppoſe him to have had as right apprehenſions of that dark and ſilent ſtate, as any Man) utters theſe expreſſions—<hi>The grave cannot praiſe thee; death cannot ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate thee; they that go down to the pit cannot hope for thy Truth</hi>—. <note place="margin">Iſa. 38. 18, 19.</note> What can be underſtood by that Scripture Metaphor—<hi>as the Tree falls, ſo it ſhall lye, whether,</hi>—&amp;c. but that this Life is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acceptable time, the only day of Salvation—, <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 2.</note> and if once paſs'd, is irrecoverable for ever; and that death when ever it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103796:7"/> ſtrips us of theſe Tabernacles, will fix our Souls in an unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſtate, either of Happineſs or Miſery, according to the bent of our hearts and lives in this World? And notwithſtanding <hi>T. M</hi>'s. ſophiſtical Inference and confident Concluſions, I heartily wiſh that neither he, nor any others, may neglect the great and eſſential work of Faith, whilſt converſant in the paths of time; leſt a future remembrance of the preſent opportunity prove an aggravation of Torment, when all hope and comfort ſhall be cut off for ever.</p>
               <p>Secondly; 'Tis very abſurd to imagine that Faith ſhall be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Souls already poſſeſſed of an eternal ſtate, ſince this imperfect ſtate of Mortality is the only proper time for the exerciſe of it. Faith is indeed the moſt pretious Jewel to poor bewildred Mortals on this ſide <hi>Jordan.</hi> Hereby they may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times (like <hi>Moſes</hi> from the top of <hi>Piſgah</hi>) get a glimpſe of the promiſed <hi>Canaan</hi> for their preſent conſolation and ſupport, whilſt ſojourning in the Tents of <hi>Kedar</hi>—. <note place="margin">Pſalm.</note> But when they are once ſafely arriv'd on the other ſide, and have reach'd the ſweet Air of the upper Regions, leaving behind all the filthy Garments and heavy cloggs of corruption, Faith, which was before ſo valuable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſwallowed up in fruition; and they will no more need or make uſe of it, than a Man reſtor'd to perfect ſtrength will the Crutches with which he was formerly ſupported in an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental Lameneſs. And for ſuch as dye wholly without Faith, what middle ſtate ſhall we imagine them to be lodg'd in, that can capacitate them for the exerciſe of this eſſential Grace? Since the Scriptures mention but two Receptacles for the ſpirits of all Men, when diſlodg'd from their earthly Priſons; <hi>viz.</hi> the eternal boſom of Divine Love, where Faith ceaſes, as having at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd its end; and the Society of accurſed Angelical Spirits; where Faith, if preſent, could not be leſs unſuitable? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, waving further Arguments in ſo clear a caſe, I proceed to conſider the third Aſſertion, of the ſame blaſphemous ſtrain, often repeated in the ſeveral Writings of the ſaid <hi>T. M. viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
                  <hi>That there is no Hell or future ſtate of Eternal Puniſhment; but by thoſe terms we are to underſtand only the troubles of this Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ſeems needleſs to enumerate the many undeniable Teſtimonies in holy Writ, for clearing the certainty of a future eternal Puniſhment: Since nothing can be more plain, though <hi>T. M.</hi> is not afraid to ſmooth over with inconſiſtent Gloſſes ſome of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103796:7"/> the moſt Remarkable; <note place="margin">Luke 16.</note> as the Parable of <hi>Dives</hi> and <hi>Lazarus</hi> and of the Goats on the left Hand Sentenced to everlaſting Puniſhment; <note place="margin">Mal. 25. <hi>ult.</hi> verſe 41.</note> together with the Form of that dreadful Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,—<hi>Depart from me ye Curſed into everlaſting Fire, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Devil and his Angels</hi>:—The Advice to Pluck a right Eye, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> rather than to have the whole Man caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell Fire, where the Worm dieth not, and the Fire is not quenched:—The Lake of Fire and Brimſtone, mentioned in the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> into which all whoſe Names are not written in the Book of Life ſhall be caſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—All which, he will have to be no more than Bugbears to frighten the World, or at moſt but figurative Expreſſions to ſignifie the Troubles of this Life. His ſuggeſting a Double Eternity [or everlaſting] <hi>Clav. Aur.</hi> p. 12. one during the Continuance of the Body on Earth, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hereafter in the unbodied State; is ſo ridiculous, as alſo his Application, that it needs no Anſwer. Without running into nice Diſputes about the Locality of Hell, or the Kind of Fire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (which are at beſt, but oppoſing Humane Reaſon to Divine Wiſdom and Authority, and a very dangerous Step to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Atheiſm.) It is moſt certain, from the whole Scope and Harmony of the ſacred Records both of all the old and new Teſtament, that there is a real, not imaginary Hell, or State of eternal Puniſhment allotted to all obſtinate and finally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent Sinners: And whether we ought to eſteem the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of unqueſtionable Verity, a Cheat, and Chriſt himſelf (who is the Way, the Truth and the Life) <note place="margin">Joh. 14. 6.</note> an Impoſtor, or <hi>T. M.</hi> is not difficult to Determine. But,</p>
               <p>Firſt, If there be no other Hell than the Troubles of this Life, Then the moſt eminent Servants of God, have generally been the greateſt Objects of his Wrath, and many of the moſt hardened Sinners felt little or nothing of it. What do we find more frequent, than that the beſt of Gods Children have been moſt ſorely exerciſed with Afflictions in this Life, and yet out of a gracious End, and as a Badge of his Paternal Love—, <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 6, 7. Rev. 3. 19.</note> to Purge away their Droſs, that they may come forth as try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Gold—and be better fitted for the higheſt Manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Grace and Favour: whilſt others who make choice of their good things in this Life have been ſuffered to go on in an uninterrupted Courſe of ſenſual Pleaſures without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Check, Croſſes or Calamities to the Period of their Lives? Something of this Nature the Royal Pſalmiſt obſerved; and records as a ſtumbling Block to him for a time, <hi>When</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:103796:8"/> 
                  <hi>he beheld their Eyes ſtanding out with Fatneſs—; That they were not in Trouble,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but had more than their Hearts could Wiſh, whilst he was plagued all the Day long, and chaſtened every Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> But when he went into the Sanctuary, and there Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed his Intereſt in God, he knew the Reaſon of theſe differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſpenſations; that the former had but a miſerable Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that his, though attended with the Croſs, was far more Elegible: Therefore in the Concluſion, he Addreſſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to God. <note place="margin">Pſalm 73. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 14, 15, 23, 24.</note> —<hi>Nevertheleſs I am continually with thee, thou haſt upholden me by my right Hand; thou ſhalt Lead me by thy Counſel, and afterwards Receive me to Glory</hi>—.'Tis moſt certain, that the Sufferings of this Life in the higheſt Degree which Chriſtians can Experience, are not worthy to be compared with their future Glory—; <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 18.</note> and therefore they have Cauſe to bleſs God inſtead of Murmuring or Repining: Yet, to Imagine that ſuch ſhall be Coheirs of the ſame eternal Happineſs, who not only enjoy the Quietneſs of this World's imaginary Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, but Live and Die in an unregenerate Courſe, wholly void both of reſtraining and ſanctifying Grace, is to make them the ſpecial Favourites of God; and does much more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate from divine Goodneſs and Purity, than to Believe that he will Inflict infinite Puniſhment for finite Sins; for the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is not only warranted in and by the Scriptures, but 'tis agreeable to right Reaſon; That the abſolute Soveraign and Creator of all things, ſhould Impoſe ſuch Laws upon his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures either as to Rewards or Puniſhments, as ſeem beſt to his own unſearchable Wiſdom and Pleaſure. Such Fooliſh and Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Arguings as ſeem to Impeach, Limit or Direct the Supream Being, are briefly yet ſufficiently Refuted by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 20, 21. 2 Col. 2. 8.</note> and may be ranked with that dangerous Philoſophy and vain Deceit, againſt which he gives a ſeaſonable Caution.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Next to an impartial Search into the Divine Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, (too much neglected and no leſs perverted) I would wiſh <hi>T. M.</hi> and every other Perſon, that does but ſo much as Heſitate at the Belief of a future Puniſhment, to make it their Buſineſs to Converſe with ſuch dying Perſons, as have been moſt negligent in the great Concerns of another Life; and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially with the moſt bold and daring Atheiſts, (who turn all Religion into Ridicule, and by a kind of Infernal Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy which their grand Maſter is always ready to furniſh them with, appear as Champions not for, but againſt the Truth; whilſt the feeble <hi>Nexus</hi> of Health, or uninterrupted Union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103796:8"/> Soul and Body laſts, and they can Swim in temporal Pleaſures:) Such heſitating Perſon or Perſons may then, if not Caſe-hardened, chance to meet with ſome more effectual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions, than whilſt they are partially Buſied in defending their own erroneous Notions. When the dark Shades of Death ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and the Soul apprehending the nearneſs of its inevitable Separation, hath the cleareſt Idea's of things, and can no longer be cajol'd into a ſervile Compliance with the Organs of Senſe, then is the fitteſt time to mark its Apprehenſions of a future State. As ſome have anticipated the Joys of Heaven, and been ſo brim-full at the Soul's taking its flight from this earthly Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that they could ſcarce contain it: So, many others who in the Series of their Lives have ſeemed wholly void both of the Fear and Belief of a future Hell, have had ſuch plentiful foretaſts of it in their own Breaſts, and ſo powerfully preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to others, as was ſufficient to have overcome the moſt Stoical Apathy in any Spectator. How have they then Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed their own former Principles and Practice with the moſt paſſionate Clamours, the bittereſt Reflections, and the evident Tokens of Intollerable Torments! What would they not then give for a little Reſpite, to Convince the World as well by Practice as Words of their former Miſtake! What a diſmal thing muſt it needs be with ſuch inexpreſſible Horrour, and as it were, the Beginnings of Hell, to Lanch forth into the Ocean of Eternity! Then there will be a certain, but a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Conviction of all thoſe, who now either profeſſedly or practically diſregard a future Puniſhment, though they may at preſent ſeem ſo Confirmed in their Stupidity, as not only to Reject <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, &amp;c. but if poſſible, a Meſſenger from the Dead.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>The next Erroneous Aſſertion to be Examined, is,</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>That Man in his Primitive Innocency hath not, nor now hath, in any meaſure a free Will or Choice in himſelf: But that</hi> Adam<hi>'s Fall and the greateſt particular Tranſgreſſions ever ſince were by Divine Predeſtination and Compulſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That our firſt Parents in their primitive State of Paradiſical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, were endowed with a freedom of Will or Choice, in reſpect to their Obedience or Diſobedience to the Divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; and though not abſolutely free Agents becauſe under the Limitation of a righteous Law, (not impoſſible to be performed)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103796:9"/> were in no wiſe conſtrain'd to Violate or Infringe it, without their own voluntary Deviation; and that God, the Fountain of all Grace and Goodneſs, though in his unſearchable Wiſdom and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Foreſight, permitting and providing an Expiation for Sin, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was, nor could be in any reſpect the efficient or impulſive Cauſe thereof, is very agreeable to the Scope of the holy Scriptures, and the ſenſe of the antient Chriſtians. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Orig. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ. lib.</hi> 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> But this Doctrine it ſeems is ſtrange to <hi>T. M.</hi> who tells us in his <hi>Myſt. of Iniq. p.</hi> 24. That he cannot imagine or believe that God could certainly foreſee <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall, if an equal power was given him to ſtand or fall; and the reaſon he gives, is becauſe he [<hi>viz. T. M.</hi>] cannot plant in his Mind any Idea of the way and manner of ſuch foreſight. Doubtleſs they who will attempt to meaſure out Infinite Wiſdom, Knowledge, Power, or any other of the Divine Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes by the narrow limits of depraved Reaſon, had better never med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with things of ſo ſublime a nature. And indeed 'tis much more ſafe and commendable, not only for ſuch, but for all perſons, to avoid prying too curiouſly into the unſearchable depths of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Counſels, the Eternal Eſſence, Purpoſes and Decrees of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible Trinity, as alſo their wonderful manifeſtations in time in the myſterious work of Creation and Redemption; whereby 'tis ſo eaſie for frail Man, whilſt blinded with the thick foggs of theſe lower Regions, and eſpecially without great caution and humility, to run into a Labyrinth of Errour, and juſt that God ſhould ſuffer him ſo to do. Without ſoaring ſo high after ſpeculative Knowledge, we have ſufficient ground for admiration and praiſe, whilſt we conſider That the Tree of Life is not wholly loſt; that God hath not left Mankind in this miſerable eſtate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> altogether deſtitute of help and hope; <note place="margin">Col. 1. 15. Eph. 2. 20. Rev. 3. 14. Col. 1 16. John 1. 3. Rom. 5. 15. 16, 17, 18 19. Mat. 11 28.</note> that he who was the <hi>firſt born</hi> of every Creature, <hi>the corner ſtone</hi>—, the beginning of the Greation of God—, by and for whom all things were made—, is alſo the Reſtorer of the fallen ſtate of Mankind; that he is indifferently exhibited to all (both Jews and Gentiles) as the free Gift of Divine Love, and not only invites eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Soul that is weary and heavy laden to come unto him for Reſt, but is both able and willing to ſave to the uttermoſt all that come unto God through him. In a large acceptati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n he is the Saviour of all Men, by purchaſing that gracious and general Reprieve be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hinted at, and not only upholding the ſinful State of this World, but exhibiting the Terms of Salvation indifferently unto all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and ſetting them, as it were, once more upon their own Feet, in a way of temporary Probation: And to all thoſe, who from the ſinful Life of fallen Nature, attain not only to the reſtored Life of Reaſon, but become united to him by Faith and Love
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103796:9"/> (which neceſſarily include Obedience) he is an effectual Saviour. Thus far all agree: But then what unhappy Controverſies have enſued, about the extent of the humane Power and Capacity, in moving towards embracing or improving the Means of Grace thus freely offered. And whilſt ſome are ready to center all in the ſtrength of Man's natural Will, and ſo to make him a compleat <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, both as to the firſt reception and progreſſive Acts of Faith: <hi>T. M.</hi> with an unparallel'd boldneſs runs into the contrary Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and would have him but a meer Machine, wholly deſtitute of Will, Power, Choice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or at leaſt of the voluntary Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of all thoſe ennobling Endowments (tho' rectified by, and made ſubſervient to a ſupernatural Principle of Divine Grace) and in all his Efforts towards good or evil, acted meerly by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion and fatal Neceſſity.</p>
               <p>He affirms [<hi>Myſt. of Iniq.</hi> p. 30.]—<hi>Judas</hi> inevitably betrayed Chriſt, and deſtroyed himſelf—: And [<hi>ibid.</hi>]—Men are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated and compelled to die in Unbelief, before they are born—; And—Blaſphemies, Murthers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are compelled on Men—[Addit. to <hi>Clav. Aurea.</hi> p. 21.] When the grand Enemy of Mankind can no longer hold the World in Atheiſm and open Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility againſt the exhibited Means of Salvation, he will not ſtick to put on a more plauſible diſguiſe, but like an Angel of Light transforms himſelf into any ſhape, that he may, if poſſible, carry on his own Work with equal Succeſs: And no wonder if he drive unwary and aſpiring Man, whilſt reſting in his own Wiſdom, into many dangerous Deluſions. What need is there of ſoaring ſo high into the Arcana of Heaven, or to ravel the Divine Councils for Predeſtination, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſince all things eſſential to Faith and Practice are made plain, and by a wonderful Condeſcention, ſuited to the meaneſt Capacity; if Man will but firſt lay aſide that over-wiſe Serpentine Subtilty, which is the proper effect of the forbidden Fruit, and with a genuine Sincerity ſubmit to the Divine Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? The former is that infernal Wiſdom, branded by St. <hi>James</hi> with the Epithetes of ſenſual and develiſh; <note place="margin">Jame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 15.</note> which always either wholly rejected or perverted the true Simplicity of the Goſpel, and tends to nothing but Strife, Diſcord and Confuſion: <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 19, 20, 21.</note> The latter is of an higher and more noble Extract, takes the Word of God upon its own Authority, ſilences all Carnal Reaſonings, compares the more abſtruſe Part with what is more plain, and always tends to Union, Love and Harmony.</p>
               <p>As to what <hi>T. M.</hi> ſo often blaſphemouſly urges of God's being the Author or poſitive Cauſe of all and every particular ſin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo many far more Learned Pens, having ſufficiently cleared that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103796:10"/> Point and ſolv'd all <hi>T. M</hi>'s Objections, which he deduces from Scripture (as the hardning of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> &amp;c.) to touch thereupon ſeems but <hi>actum agere,</hi> and therefore rather to be omitted in ſo brief a Diſcourſe as this. That the Omnipotent Creator could have anticipated Mans Fall, and endow'd him with an unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Perfection, never liable to fall or be corrupted, is paſt all Queſtion; but that it pleaſed the unſearchable Wiſdom of the Supream Being, to place him in a mutable Station, pronouncing Happineſs or Miſery upon ſuch and ſuch Conditions, and certainly foreſeeing his voluntary Deviation to provide an All-ſufficient <hi>Medium,</hi> for his recovery (thereby centring the whole Work of Salvation in the Riches of Free-Grace, by and through a Redeemer) ſhould lead us to the higheſt Returns of Love and Gratitude that we are capable of, and not into Critical, much leſs Senſorious Animadverſions. What the Fall of Angels was, what the Cauſe thereof, and why Irreparable; as alſo by what means the bleſſed Ones were ſuſtained, are Points almoſt too lofty to meddle with, eſpecially ſince not very material to the preſent purpoſe. Though the Eternal Fountain and Primary Cauſe of all things muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to have perfectly foreſeen, as it were, <hi>uno intuitu,</hi> all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Motions and Events before the birth of Time; it will not thence follow, that he muſt be the efficient or enforcing Cauſe of Sin. He is indeed after a ſort, the <hi>Cauſa ſine quâ non;</hi> for without him, Angels and Men had never had a Being, and conſequently never ſinn'd: Yet this can in no wiſe make him the poſitive Cauſe. Sin is a <hi>Non-entity</hi> (at leaſt till committed) a privation, defect, diſorder, or preternatural State of rational Beings; as might be illuſtrated from many plain and familiar Compariſons. 'Tis ſometimes repreſented by Darkneſs; and what poſitive Cauſe is there of that? When the Sun recedes from our Hemiſphere, the Night and Darkneſs enſue; and muſt the Sun therefore be the Cauſe of Darkneſs? The Supream Being having no Law but his immenſe Perfections, can no more ſwerve from his own rectitude than ceaſe to be. That there is an admirable Connexion in the whole Courſe of his Providence, not inconſiſtent with the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Liberty, yet ſtill harmoniouſly accompliſhing his immutable Decrees: That all kinds of <hi>ataxy quoad hominem,</hi> proceed from the Free-Actings of the Humane Will, yet by Divine Permiſſion: That God forces not the Will in Converſion, but by a ſupernatural Work graciouſly inclines it; yet neither forces nor inclines the Heart in any meaſure to ſin, but only leaves it to that corrupt Frame and thoſe vicious Habits wherein 'tis ſettled: And that there is an excellent agreement between the Primary and all ſecond
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103796:10"/> Cauſes, to the glory of the Divine Juſtice, as well as the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable Riches of Free Grace, hath been ſo amply and learnedly Diſcuſs'd by others, that to inſiſt further thereupon would ſavour highly of Oſtentation.</p>
               <p>From our Saviour's Parable of the Talents, and an impartial comparing of many other parallel Scriptures, 'tis moſt evident that God's expectations of obediential Returns from every Man, are proportioned to the meaſure of Grace which he gives; and that the faithful Improvement of that meaſure, is not only accepted by him, but attended with greater enlargements from his inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſtible Fulneſs: Whereas the neglect or miſ-improvement of that meaſure, though never ſo ſmall, (as in the caſe of the ſingle Talent) cauſes the open hand of Divine Bounty to be withdrawn, all gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Experiences to wither and vaniſh, and gradually leaves the Soul to an obdurate <hi>Frame,</hi> under the juſt Sentence of Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Man therefore, in reſpect to his own Happineſs or Miſery, either Temporal or Eternal, is not ſo much a Machine or meerly paſſive, as <hi>T. M.</hi> would inſinuate; nor is he in any wiſe compell'd to make this or that choice. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. de Civit. Dei, lib</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 30. <hi>Anſelm de concord. grat. &amp; liberi arbitrii.</hi>
                  </note> For though he hath not a natural ſtrength or capacity to find out, chooſe and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in the narrow path that leads to Eternal Life; yet he hath a Talent ſupernatural, a common Gift or meaſure of Grace freely beſtowed on him, as an Univerſal Benefit, accruing by and from the ſecond <hi>Adam;</hi> which ſo far as he reſigns or ſubjects to his ſenſual part, he wilfully ſhuts the Door of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon himſelf: But if he faithfully improve this ſingle Talent, by denying his ſenſual Luſts and the dictates of depraved Reaſon, and becomes ſincerely reſign'd to the Divine Conduct; then to him that thus hath (<hi>i. e.</hi> rightly uſeth) more ſhall be given, and he ſhall have abundance; <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 29.</note> like a Branch abiding in the true Vine, he ſhall be always fruitful, through ſpiritual Vertue convey'd from that Eternal Root; and thus growing from ſtrength to ſtrength, ſhall at laſt (as the Royal Prophet ſaith) appear before God in <hi>Zion.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtin. de cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt. &amp; grat. c.</hi> 14. <hi>Id. Enchirid. ad Laurent. cap.</hi> 103</note> That the tenders of Divine Grace, which are univerſally extenſive, do not prove univerſally effectual, muſt be imputed to the perverſneſs of Mans Heart, which obſtinately oppoſes the way of Life and Happineſs, and reſting in that ſerpentine Wiſdom, before hinted, forms to himſelf ſome vain and deluſive Ideas inſtead thereof; ſo that (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet poſitively affirms in the caſe of rebellious <hi>Iſrael</hi>) <note place="margin">Hoſ. 13. 9.</note> his deſtruction is only of and from himſelf.</p>
               <p>If <hi>T. M.</hi> thinks I put too great Streſs upon the Parable of the Talents, becauſe 'twas but a Parable and not a Reality (as he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103796:11"/> in divers Places againſt the Parable of <hi>Dives</hi> and <hi>Lazarus;</hi> of the Sheep and the Goats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) He may remember, that 'twas our Saviours delight to exhibit in Parables the greateſt Myſteries of his Kingdom, yet not leaving thoſe familiar Compariſons ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, but that the meaneſt Capacity might apprehend his gracious Deſign therein; for we ſcarce read of any that ſtumbled at them, but the over-wiſe and ſelf-confident, to whoſe lofty expectations indeed they were not ſo well adapted; nor may we any more ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that he did or would thereby impoſe deſtructive Fallacies upon loſt Mankind whom he came to ſave, than joyn with the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Phariſees in cenſuring him for an Impoſtor, Blaſphemer, or poſſeſs'd with an Evil-Spirit. The ſweetneſs of his Deportment and Condeſcention in explaining, inculcating and applying what he delivered, did ſufficiently evince that his Parables were of great weight, that he had no deſign thereby to amuſe or deceive his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors; but on the contrary, that believing they might have Life through him. <note place="margin">Joh. 5. 40. cap. 7. 37. cap. 10. 9.</note> But the next thing in <hi>T. M</hi>'s new Syſteme of Divinity is,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>Fifithly; <hi>That the Children of the Fleſh</hi> (Rom. 9. 8.) <hi>are all Men in the Fleſh, whether good or evil; and the Children of the Promiſe are the Souls of all Men that ever were, are, or ſhall be (not one excepted of what Nation or Belief ſoever) in their ſeparated or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodied State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is indeed agreeable with his Doctrine of univerſal inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Salvation, and equally true. That the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in this and many other concurring Places intended to diſtinguiſh two kinds of Perſons, as vaſtly differing in their Principles, Practices and Ends, as light and darkneſs, is evident beyond all reaſonable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. How often do we find him uſing <hi>Iſmael</hi> (<hi>Abraham</hi>'s Son by the Bondwoman) as a Type of the unregenerate part of Mankind; and <hi>Iſaac</hi> the promiſed Heir, as a lively Repreſentative of all thoſe who truly lay hold on the Promiſes of God by Faith, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther under the Legal or Evangelical Diſpenſation (the Object of Faith being ſtill the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Meſſiah!</hi>) And that he limits the true <hi>Iſrael</hi> or Seed of Promiſe to the latter, <hi>i. e.</hi> the faithful and obedient Servants of God, and not to the Lineage of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> deſcending from him in <hi>Iſaac</hi> by natural Generation; is alſo clear from the ſcope of the foregoing Verſes. When he had firſt teſtified his unparallel'd Sorrow for the obſtinate Blindneſs of the literal <hi>Iſrael,</hi> reckoned up thoſe tranſcendent Priviledges wherewith they were dignified beyond all other Nations, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Priority of Right to the Goſpel; he tells us, That the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103796:11"/> Word of God hath not been altogether ineffectual, though for the moſt part, rejected by theſe natural Branches; <note place="margin">verſe 6.</note> and adds a Reaſon—<hi>For all are not</hi> Iſrael <hi>that are of</hi> Iſrael: <hi>neither becauſe the Seed of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham <hi>are they his Children; but in</hi> Iſaac <hi>ſhall thy Seed be called</hi>—: And leſt any ſhould think he meant only the literal Off-ſpring of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> he explains himſelf further <note place="margin">verſe 7.</note> —That is, <hi>they who are the Children of the Fleſh are not the Children of God, but the Children of the Promiſe.</hi>—&amp;c. If <hi>Iſaac</hi> therefore (once intentionally Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed, and in whom all the Nations of the Earth were to be Bleſſed) be conſidered as a Type of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael</hi> will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be all thoſe who are truly obedient to the Faith of the Goſpel; and the Children of the Fleſh all thoſe (whether Jews or Gentiles) who either remain in the groſs Pollutions of unſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Nature, or exalt the imperfect typical Righteouſneſs of the Law in oppoſition to Chriſt the end thereof. Thus much ſeems plainly imported in the Apoſtles reſult <note place="margin">verſes 30, 31, 32.</note> —<hi>The Gentles have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to the Righteouſneſs of Faith</hi>—; <hi>but</hi> Iſrael <hi>hath not attained to the Law of Righteouſneſs—; becauſe they ſought it not by Faith, but by the works of the Law</hi>—; which he further clears <note place="margin">cap. 10. v. 4.</note> —<hi>For Chriſt is the end of the Law for Righteouſneſs to every one that believeth.</hi> The ſame learned Apoſtle in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians</hi> (who were ready to look back from the ennobling Principle of Faith, to the ſandy Foundation of the Law) more largely illuſtrates this Point in ſeveral Chapters, and after a very copious diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between the fleſhly and ſpiritual Seed, lays down this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Concluſion. <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 29. cap. 4. 28.</note> —<hi>If ye be Chriſt's then are ye</hi> Abraham<hi>'s Seed and Heirs according to promiſe.</hi> But let us conſider a little how this agrees with <hi>T. M</hi>'s. Sophiſtical Invention [Second Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to <hi>Clav. Aur.</hi> pag. 29.]—That all Men are damn'd or loſt in the Fleſh, and all Men are ſaved in the Spirit—. And [<hi>Clav. Aur.</hi> p. 10.]—The Children of the Fleſh are all Men in the Fleſh, Good or Evil; and—<hi>&amp;c.</hi> as before recited. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth not ſay, We are now the Children of the Fleſh, but in the other World we ſhall be the Children and Heirs of Promiſe: Nor doth Chriſt tell the obſtinate and unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Jews, whom he pronounces Children of the Devil, <note place="margin">Joh. 8. 44</note> that they ſhould hereafter be the Heirs of Promiſe; but declares poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, that whither he went they could not come: Neither doth St. <hi>John</hi> ſay,—We ſhall hereafter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 2.</note> but—Beloved, <hi>now are we the Sons of God,</hi> now, in this preſent State of imperfection, whilſt we are clogged with the relicts of Sin; tho' as born of God we ſin not [<hi>i. e.</hi> not by choice and approbation; not by habitual Subjection, nor by Guilt's imputation:] <note place="margin">cap. 1. v 8. cap. 5. v. 18.</note> and tho' we have this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103796:12"/> of being now the adopted Children of God (in diſtinction from the unregenerate World, which lies in Wickedneſs, <note place="margin">Verſe 19.</note> 
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually enſlaved to Satan the wicked One) yet we have higher enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in reverſion than our preſent minority is capable of, knowing that when he (who is our Life, our Head, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him. The next thing to be examined is,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>Sixthly; <hi>That</hi> Elijah, <hi>propheſied by</hi> Malachi, <hi>is yet to come; and that</hi> T. M. <hi>(though in ſome places ſeemingly modeſt and cautious) is that very perſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the <hi>Elias</hi> or Harbinger foretold by <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 40. 3, 4</note> agrees with this of <hi>Malachi,</hi> and was, at leaſt, partly fulfill'd by the Coming and Miniſtry of <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> is paſt all contradiction; ſince no leſs than Chriſt himſelf plainly decides it in the affirmative—; <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 7, 8. to the 15 v. ch. 17. v. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>This is that</hi> Elias <hi>which was to come</hi> (having before ſpoken of <hi>John</hi>): and afterwards—<hi>Elias is come already</hi>—. But whether there may not be a ſecond Coming of <hi>Elias</hi> to forewarn and prepare the ſtupid World for Chriſt's ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Coming (becauſe <hi>Malachi</hi> deſcribes a very terrible day ſucce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daneous to <hi>Elijah</hi>'s coming, <note place="margin">Mal. 4. 1, 2. 3, 5. Rev. 14. 6.</note> wherein the wicked ſhould be conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,) I dare not determine; having never pretended to Criticiſm, much leſs Infallibility, in what is left obſcure. But ſuppoſing a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of that (which very learned men have thought probable) I think I may very ſafely conclude that <hi>T. M.</hi> cannot be the perſon; and that for ſeveral Reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt; Becauſe it muſt be ſuppoſed that the Teſtimony of this emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Prophet (<hi>viz. Elijah</hi> or <hi>Elias</hi>) will be conſonant to, or at leaſt conſiſtent with <hi>Malachi</hi>'s Prophecy, which hath a ſpecial reſpect to, and ſeems as it were calculated for the time of his manifeſtation. Now <hi>Malachi</hi> ſpeaks of a remarkable deciſion between the righteous and the wicked, and of their ſeveral rewards as different as their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples—; that Chriſt the Meſſenger of the Covenant ſhould come ſuddenly to his Temple, and that the former ſhould then be owned and valued by him as his Jewels—; <note place="margin">Mal. 3. 1, 2, 3, 4, 16, 17, 18. ver. 12th.</note> that all Nations ſhould call them bleſſed—; <note place="margin">ch. 4. v. 2.</note> that the Sun of Righteouſneſs ſhould ariſe unto them with healing under his wings—: But the latter, <hi>i. e.</hi> the wicked, ſhould be trodden down as Aſhes under their feet, and conſumed like Stubble in that day which ſhould burn as an Oven—; <note place="margin">ch. 4. v. 1, 3.</note> and then it follows, that <hi>Elijah</hi> the Prophet ſhall be ſent before this great and dreadful day of the Lord.— <note place="margin">verſe 5.</note> But <hi>T. M.</hi> ranks the wicked and the righteous together, as to their future reward, thereby contradicting the ſcope of <hi>Malachi,</hi> and conſequently cannot be the Prophet intended by him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Becauſe, when Scripture Prophecies have a double ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment, there is uſually ſome Harmony or Proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103796:12"/> the ſeveral times, as alſo, the ſcope, nature and manner of their reſpective conſummation. Thus there are many Prophecies that directly, or as it were, ſpecifically refer to the return of the two Tribes and half from their ſeventy Years Captivity, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>building of the Temple; which alſo, tho' more remotely, point at the flouriſhing State of Chriſt's Kingdom, when he ſhall (as <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachi</hi> ſaith) come to his Temple, <hi>i. e.</hi> collective Body of his Saints. Now this twofold accompliſhment doth thus far harmonize; in the former there was an eminent Reformation, a careful peruſing the Records of the Law, and a reeſtabliſhing the purity of Gods worſhip, under the happy conduct of <hi>Ezra, Nehemiah,</hi> &amp;c. And in the latter there will be a perfection of Holineſs, beyond all preſent Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons. Likewiſe, if a double accompliſhment be aſſign'd to this Prophecy of <hi>Elijah</hi>'s coming, <hi>viz. John</hi> the forerunner of Chriſt in his Incarnation, and ſome other eminent Meſſenger to precede his ſecond glorious Coming; <hi>John</hi>'s Miniſtry we know ſtrictly enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Repentance as eſſential to Salvation, branding thoſe he judged moſt refractory for a generation of Vipers, and ſo cloſely laid the Ax to the Root, that he denounces Deſtruction to all that did not bring forth good Fruit—; <note place="margin">Mal 3. 1, 2, 3, 6, 7, 8, 10,</note> nor may we ſuppoſe that a ſecond <hi>Elias</hi> will be more remiſs, or not enjoyn Repentance and Faith, as eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Qualifications to meet Chriſt at his next coming. But <hi>T. M.</hi> ſuggeſting a certainty of Salvation to all that live and die in Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency and Unbelief, ſeems of all Men that ever yet appear'd upon the Stage of this World, the moſt unqualified to be that Prophet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>Therefore, Laſtly, A Word or two to his extraordinary Viſions (as he will have them) by which he overcame his former reluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy, and was in ſome meaſure ſettled in the Belief of his being the <hi>Elias, &amp;c.</hi> [p. 13, 14, 15, 16, <hi>of his Diſp. concerning</hi> Elijah.]</p>
               <p>The particulars of his Viſions, which he mentions, are 1. A Globe of tranſparent Fire, about the bigneſs of the Moon at full; from whence proceeded the form of a Sword, and at the end thereof Flames of Fire. Afterwards a Dove vaniſhing out of his Sight. And laſtly, an univerſal and prodigious Comet, in the Year 1680/1.</p>
               <p>As for the two former, that they might be the <hi>Chimera</hi>'s of a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly and overthoughtful Brain, is not very improbable, from the many inſtances which Authentick Hiſtory affords; and that only in reſpect to a deprav'd diſpoſition of the Blood and Spirits: but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally what ſtrange deluſions may not Men run into, when confiding in their own ſtrength they Soar too high and tempt the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection to be withdrawn! But ſuppoſing them to be real, what ground can any Man, rightly poſſeſs'd of Reaſon, gather from thence for ſuch extraordinary Concluſions? Perhaps any one that hath
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:103796:13"/> read of Meteors and their Production might eaſily ſolve the Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomenon of the fiery Globe by natural cauſes, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Viz.</hi> Nitro-ſulphureous Particles of Air driven together by the exhal'd moiſture of the Earth, and then fir'd by the attraction of Calorifick Atoms.</note> without running into ſuch preſumptuous and unaccountable ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. But that which ſeems to be of greateſt ſtreſs with <hi>T. M.</hi> is, That theſe particular Viſions happend to him at ſuch times as he was moſt wavering, and ſo beſet with clouds of Diffidence that he could not be ſatisfied without Miracles; and not only ſo, but the Dove was the very kind of Viſion which he had with a ſtrange curioſity imagin'd to himſelf, and as it were deſir'd for the confirmation of his Faith. Now, granting all this, what can be more reaſonable, than that Man wilfully leaving or perverting the ways of God, and the Rules preſcribed by him, ſhould be given up to the ſtrong Deluſions of Satan? <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 4. Epheſ. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> And why may not the titular God of this world, the Prince of the Power of the Air, be permitted to ſhew ſomething extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary for the promoting his own work in the World? Why may he not exert the utmoſt of his limited power near the period of his infernal Kingdom? <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 13, 14, 15. 2 Theſ. 2. 8, 9, 10. Mat. 24. 23, 24, 25.</note> Eſpecially ſince we are not only cautioned againſt his moſt plauſible Angelical Transformations, but aſſured that he will in the latter days do great things by his Emiſſaries con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed with Signs and Wonders to deceive, if poſſible, the very E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect? So that theſe Miracles rather afford ground of Suſpicion than confirmation of <hi>T. M</hi>'s new Hypotheſis: And I would heartily wiſh him to conſider with all poſſible humility and ſeriouſneſs, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that heavy and repeated <hi>Anathema</hi> denonunced by St. <hi>Paul</hi> againſt ſuch as ſhould dare to Preach any new Goſpel, <note place="margin">1 Gal. 8. 9.</note> may not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to all thoſe that ſtrenuouſly endeavour to pervert the old: and whether we have not incurr'd thoſe dreadful Sanctions in the cloſe of <hi>John</hi>'s <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 22. 18, 19.</note> againſt adding to, or detracting from that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruce Philoſophy; ſince he hath been ſo bold to explode the Lake of Fire and ſecond Death, therein often mentioned.</p>
               <p>If he dare think me his Friend, and is yet capable of weighing things impartially, for I would charitably hope his Error is more ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his Judgement than his Will, the beſt Advice I can give, is, inſtead of defending, ſpeedily to recede from theſe his imbib'd Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with ſuch Teſtimony of profound humility as we read of in the Caſe of <hi>Job</hi> (who doubtleſs, had far leſs need of it, tho' not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excuſable from an extream in ſelf-Juſtification) <note place="margin">Job 40. 4, 5.</note> —I will lay my Hand upon my Mouth: Once have I ſpoken, but I will not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, yea twice, but I will proceed no further:— <note place="margin">cap. 42. v. 6.</note> Wherefore I abhor my ſelf, and repent in duſt and aſhes—. This ſeems the moſt probable, if not the only way to extricate himſelf from the Gall of bitterneſs— <note place="margin">Acts 8. 23.</note> and to find Mercy in the great day of Chriſt's appearance.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:103796:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
